For as long as philosophy
has asked its first question,
existence has seemed
to call for explanation.
Why is there anything at all?
The mind reaches for a source,
a first cause,
a final reason able to account
for the whole.
There is awareness, a questioning process
in which the question appears.
That occurrence belongs to the reality
we are trying to understand.
This changes the meaning of "something."
We usually think of something as a specific
object, event, or state of affairs.
But in the deepest form of the question,
something means the totality
of whatever exists.
That totality includes the
questioner, the
question, and any answer that
might be given.
So every answer arises within the very
field it tries to explain.
A complete explanation of everything would
have to include the explanation itself.
It would have to include the act of
understanding it, the system producing
it, and the conditions
that make such production possible.
Once the explanation exists, it becomes
another part of what the explanation
must cover.
The account is therefore drawn
into self-reference.
To close over the whole,
it must include its
own occurrence as one of the
things explained.
Each attempt at final closure adds the
act of closure to the totality.
This gives the deepest question
its boundary.
The question can be asked, clarified,
and understood.
It reveals that existence contains
the question of existence.
We can ask why there is something
rather than
nothing, because we are already
within the something.
This is the precise shape of
the incompleteness.
Existence can question itself
from within.
It cannot close the case
from beyond itself.